Pavel V. Fomin

Lead Enterprise Developer

City, State: Plymouth, MN, USA
LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/in/pfomin
Email: pavel.fomin@yahoo.com

Profile

- Over 20 years of software design and development experience in diverse industry environment
- Strong expertise in Java and JEE architecture with multiple Application and Web servers

Solid RDBMS background

Skills Summary

Operating Systems Linux (Mint, Redhat, SUSE), Unix (Solaris, AIX, SCO), MS Windows

Languages Java 1.1-1.7, XML, WSDL, SQL, UML, Groovy, Bash, Perl, HTML, JavaScript,

CSS

Frameworks JSE/JEE: JDBC, JAX-WS, Web Services, JMS, JMX, EJB 3, JSP, JSTL, JSF,

Servlets, Portlets, Applets

Spring: Spring Core 2.x/3.x/4.x, MVC, JDBC Template, Security, Web Services,

Rest Template, AMQP, Spring Data, Spring Data Solr

Web: Spring MVC, Grails, SiteMesh, Freemarker, Velocity, Struts 1.x, Wicket 1.2,

Apache HttpClient, jQuery, JSON

Mobile: Android

XML: SOAP, JAXB 2.x, Apache WSS4J, Axis 1.4, Castor 0.9/1.2, JDOM

ORM: Hibernate 3.0. Gorm

Caching: Ehcache 2, Memcached 2

Logging: SLF4J, Log4j, Apache Commons Logging, Java Logging API **Testing:** JUnit, DbUnit, Mockito, EasyMock, Emma, Cobertura, Spock

Databases Oracle 7/8/9/10g/11g, MySQL, MS SQL Server, Sybase, MongoDB

Application Servers Tomcat 3/4/5/6/7, Liferay Portal Server 6.2, IBM Websphere Application Server

4/5/6/7, IBM Websphere Portal Server 6.1, OAS 10g, Resin, BEA Weblogic 4.5.1/5.1/6.1, Borland Inprise Application Server 4.x, JBoss, Apache Web Server,

Oracle Web Server 2.1.1

Tools IDE: Eclipse, RAD, WSAD, JBuilder, Emacs

Modeling: ObjectAid Eclipse Plugin, Together Control/Architect, OptimalJ, Telelogic Tau UML, Rational Rose Designer, Visio Diagram Designer, Sybase

Power Designer 6.1, Oracle Designer **Messaging:** RabbitMQ, 2lemetry, IBM MQ

Monitor/Profile: VisualVM, DynaTrace, Optimizeit

Build: Maven, Ivy, Ant, GNU Make

Continuous integration: Jenkins, Hudson, Bamboo

VM / Cloud: Vagrant, Puppet, Oracle VirtualBox, Amazon EC2

Browsers: Chrome, Firefox, MS IE

Revision Control: Git, SVN, CVS, MKS, PVCS, RCS, Visual SourceSafe 5.0/6.0

(VSS)

Bug Tracking: Jira, Redmine, Bugzilla

Code Review: GitHub, Crucible, CodeCollaborator

Agile Project Management: Jira GreenHopper, Version One, Rally, XPlanner

Wiki: Atlassian Confluence, DokuWiki

Testing: SoapUI

Methodologies Agile, SCRUM, Test Driven Development, OOAD, RUP

Industries Medical supplies, Education, Finance, Banking, E-commerce, Healthcare, Medical

Work History

Solution Design Group, Professional Services

Senior Consultant 10/2014 - Present

McKesson Medical-Surgical, Web Development

Environment: Liferay 6.2 EE, Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11g, Nutch, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.7, Spring 4.0, Solr, JSP, Freemarker, jQuery, Sass, Bourbon with Bitters and Neat, Maven, Eclipse (Luna), Emacs, CVS, Git, Jenkins, Jira

Implemented new public web site for McKesson using Liferay 6.2 EE Portal server enabling the content authors to publish changes without the application code deployment. Created several Liferay portal plugins to customize the Liferay implementation for the client. Setup the clustered site search using separate Solr server and Liferay Solr plugin. Created custom page level search implementations, first extending Liferay search infrastructure and, second using Apache Solr and Nutch directly. Created build and deployment process for the custom Liferay plugins using Jenkins and Maven. Provisioned the development and production servers with Liferay, Solr and Nutch installations.

Data Recognition Corporation, Information Services

Senior Software Developer

10/2013 - 10/2014

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, MongoDB, MySQL, MS Sql Server, OpenAM, Linux, Windows 7, Amazon EC2

Tools: JDK 1.7, Spring 3.x, SiteMesh, Groovy, Grails, Node.js, jQuery, Junit, Spock, Eclipse, Emacs, Git, GitHub, Maven, Jenkins, Vagrant, Oracle VirtualBox, Puppet, Jira

Developed new and modified existing components of the IAT, the school test creation and administration tool. Created successful OpenAM POC to implement SSO functionality across different applications using a J2EE agent and a Post Authentication Plug to inject custom roles and permissions into the JEE user principal. Developed new components of Text To Speech implementation using Node.js. Created build and deployment process for the Java, Grails and Nodejs projects using Jenkins and RPM packaging.

Object Partners, Professional Services

Senior Consultant

12/2011 - 10/2013

Menards, Web Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x (tcServer), MySQL, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, JDBC, JSP, Velocity, jQuery, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, Hibernate 3.6, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Jenkins, Redmine, CodeCollaborator

Added new features to the Menards e-commerce web site and internal web site administration tool.

PeopleNet, Backend Services

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, MySQL, MS Sql Server, Linux, Windows 7, Amazon EC2

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, RabbitMQ, 2lemetry, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Maven, Jenkins, Version One

Developed new and modified existing components of the asynchronous back-end services. Created RabbitMQ AMQP based guaranteed message delivery queuing Proof-of-Concept solution, deployed to local data center and to Amazon EC2 environment. Created facade for 2lemetry m2m rest api. Created new components for the custom load test engine to perform the load testing of the new services.

Room and Board, Web Development

Environment: JEE, Tomcat 7.x, Oracle 11, Windows 7, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.6, Spring 3.1, JDBC, JSP, SiteMesh, Freemarker 2.3, jQuery, Memcache, Ivy, Log4j, JUnit, Mockito 1.9, DbUnit 2.4, Groovy, OpenORM, Eclipse (Indigo), Emacs, SVN, Bamboo, Crucible, Jira

Developed new and modified existing components of the web site and internal web site administration tool. Focused primarily on the controller and backend services. Helped to design and implement the data versioning feature in the database schema. Created new and enhanced existing components of the UI layer using HTML, JSP, Freemarker, JavaScript and jQuery.

MoneyGram International, Systems Development

Lead Developer (Software Engineer IV)

10/2007 - 12/2011

Environment: JEE, Websphere Application Server 7.x/6.x/5.x, Tomcat 4.x/6.x, Websphere Portal 6.1, Oracle, IBM MQ, Windows XP, Linux

Tools: JDK 1.4/1.5/1.6, Spring (MVC), JSP, JSF, Portlet, Servlet, Ajax, jQuery, Wicket 1.2, Struts, JAX-WS, Axis 1.4, Ehcache 2, JDBC, XML, Ant, Log4j, JUnit, WSS4J, Castor 0.9/1.2, SoapUI, Eclipse, RAD 6/7/8, Emacs, CVS, Git, UML, Hudson, DokuWiki, Rally, XPlanner

Led the design and development of the JAX-WS based web services layer for the new Web Point of Entry system (Web POE). Created two prototypes of the new web site using JSF 2 and Spring MVC 3 frameworks. The Spring MVC based prototype became the foundation for the Web POE. Created the device authentication component using the signed java applet technology to enhance the security of the Web POE site. Demonstrated the Eclipse and Tomcat servlet container efficiency for the web development while supporting the deployment of the same code base on Websphere application server.

<u>HSBC (former Metris Companies)</u>, Enterprise Application Management

Lead J2EE Developer (Senior Consultant, Business Systems)

07/2004 -10/2007

Environment: J2EE, OAS 10g Portal, Websphere 6.x/5.x, Resin 2.x, Tomcat 4.x, Apache 1.3, Oracle 10g, IBM MQ, Windows XP, Linux (RedHat), AIX

Tools: JDK 1.4, JSP, Servlet, Struts 1.1, Spring 2.0, Hibernate 3.0, JDBC, XML, XSLT, Ant 1.6, Maven, Log4j, JUnit, Eclipse, RAD, Emacs, CVS, PVCS, MKS, Together Architect, MS Visio, UML, Optimizeit Enterprise Suite (Profiler), Bugzilla

Led the design and development effort to bring aboard a number of the business partners critical for the credit card accounts acquisition business. Created new and redesigned existing web based applications in the Internet and Intranet portal environment. Created fully automated application release and deployment management process based on Ant's templated approach and CVS. Led a number of migrations of the Internet environment from the web applications side.

Compuware Corporation, Professional Services

Senior Java Developer, Full Time Consultant

07/2001 - 07/2004

HealthPartners. Center of Health Promotion

Environment: J2EE, Bea Weblogic 6.1, Tomcat 4.27, Oracle 8.1.7, MySQL 4, MS SQL Server, Windows 2000, AIX

Tools: JDK 1.3/1.4, JSP, Servlet, Struts 1.1, JDBC, XML, XSLT, JDOM, Ant, Log4j, Eclipse, Emacs, CVS, MS Visio, UML

Redesigned old web based Health Assessment application to make it more flexible, data driven. New application had been deployed under Weblogic application server and used Oracle database as the data source. Later HA application had been refactored to work under HealthPartners custom portal environment. Also created a new web based application to collect and process data for the Weight Management Preferred Provider Program. Application had been deployed under Tomcat application server and used MySQL and MS SQL server database as the data source. Both applications were created using Struts framework.

Compuware Product Division, Software Product Development

Environment: Windows 2000, z/OS

Tools: JDK 1.4, UML, XML, JDOM, Log4j, Swing, Ant, Eclipse, Emacs, CVS, Visio

Created a generic communication driver to send data between Java client and Mainframe server. This driver, written in Java, was designed to be used by multiple software products for the client-

server communication. The data was sent and received via TCP/IP in XML format and Apache's Xerces was used for XML processing. Created the graphical request/response processing tool based on Java Swing and JDOM.

Target Corporation, E-Commerce Retail Financials

Environment: J2EE, IBM Websphere 4.02, Tomcat 3.2, Oracle 8.1.7, Solaris/NT

Tools: JDK 1.2.2/1.3, JSP, JDBC, XML, XSLT, Formula One for Java (F1J 9), Struts, Ant, WSAD, Emacs, JBuilder, Telelogic Tau UML, Visio, PVCS

Designed and developed an extendible framework for the intranet-based data retrieval system in the J2EE architecture environment on the SUN Solaris and Windows NT platforms. The main goal of the framework was to provide a consistent way of presenting e-commerce financial information on the intranet in different formats such as HTML. Excel as well as graphics.

Comsys (former Cotelligent Inc.), Professional Services

Senior Software Engineer / Systems Analyst, Full Time Consultant 11/1998 - 05/2001

Innuity, Inc. E-Commerce

Environment: J2EE, Borland Inprise Application Server, Oracle 8i, Solaris/NT

Tools: JDK 1.2, EJB 1.1, JSP, JDBC, XML, UML, Rational Rose, TogetherJ, JBuilder, Emacs, SourceSafe, GNU Make, MySQL, Bugzilla, Perl

Designed and developed Enterprise Java Beans in the J2EE multi-tier architecture environment on the SUN Solaris and Windows NT platforms for the new web site builder tool. This new application provided a web based user interface for the clients to make changes to their web sites.

Thomson Prometric, Education and Certification

Environment: J2EE, Bea Weblogic Application Server, Sybase 11.9.2, Solaris/NT

Tools: JDK 1.2, EJB 1.1, JSP, JConnect JDBC, Swing, UML, Rational Rose, Visio Diagram Designer, Sybase Power Designer 6.1, JBuilder, Emacs, SourceSafe, GNU Make, MySQL, Bugzilla, Perl

Designed and developed Enterprise Java Beans in the J2EE multi-tier architecture environment on the SUN Solaris and Windows NT platforms for new Prometric Unified Financial Module. This module was the server side business logic package that provided all the financial services for the international corporate use by any J2EE complaint services or applications.

Medtronic, Medical Devices

Environment: Apache 1.3.6 WEB Server, Oracle 7, UNIX AIX/NT

Tools: C/PRO*C, Perl, Unix RCS

Created a number of data transfer processes under UNIX AIX 4.*, Oracle environment. Created new and modified existing C/PRO*C code, KSH scripts, SQL*PLUS scripts, SQL and PL/SQL code, SQL*LOADER control files to meet new requirements. Created generic Perl CGI programs to replace old application interfaces with WEB based ones. Responsible for the Revision Control System (Unix RCS) administration.

University of Minnesota Facilities Management, Education

Environment: Oracle WEB 2.1.1, Oracle 7/8, Unix AIX 4.3/NT

Tools: JDK 1.1.7, JDBC, SQL, PL/SQL, Emacs, SourceSafe

Responsible for applications software development and optimization in Unix AIX 4.3, Windows 95/NT, Oracle 7.3.3/8.0.3 environment. Created Java applets with Oracle JDBC "thin" driver to provide access to the Oracle database via WEB. Developed a number of data transfers using PL/SQL, SQLPLUS scripting, UNIX KSH scripting and ODBC. Improved HTML documents by adding some JavaScript code for MS IExplorer 4.x and Netscape Navigator 4.x.

<u>Siemens</u>, Energy Management and Information Software Software Engineer / Systems Analyst

Contraro Enginoci / Cyclomic / maryot

07/1997 - 10/1998

Environment: Oracle 7, UNIX AIX/Solaris, NT

Tools: C, C++, PRO*C, SQL, PL/SQL, Perl, RCS

Responsible for database design, development, tuning and optimization for Spectrum, an Energy Management and Information System in UNIX AIX, SUN Solaris, Windows NT, Oracle, C/C++

environment. Served as C and Oracle expert for several large-scale projects.

Center Of Financial Technologies, Financial Software

Lead Software Developer

03/1993 - 07/1997

Environment: Oracle 7, Btrieve, Windows 95, Unix Solaris/SCO

Tools: VB 4.0/5.0, VC++ 2.0, OCI, SQL, PL/SQL, Java 1.0/1.1, SourceSafe

Responsible for technical and team leadership in design, development and deployment of large scale financial applications for banking industry. Major projects included Integrated Bank System and Smart Credit/Debit Card Payment System, "Golden Grown" distributed to over 150 banks nation wide.

Interface Inc., Application Software

Software Engineer

09/1992 - 03/1993

Environment: DOS, Novell

Tools: C, FoxPro, dBase

Designed, developed, deployed and supported automated auctions maintenance system for Energy Management Equipment Stock Exchange.

Education

Novosibirsk Technical University, Novosibirsk, Russia

M.S. in Computer Science and B.S. in Mathematics, 1992

Evaluated by International Education Evaluation, Inc. (March 10, 1997. REF # 116-0369)

Oracle University

Oracle Application Server Administration course, 2005

Red Hat, Inc.

RH033 - Red Hat Linux Essentials, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 course, 2005

Red Hat, Inc.

RH133 - System Administration, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 course, 2005

Successfully completed all Red Hat Certified Technician program requirements and is certified as a Red Hat Certified Technician, Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4.

The George Washington University School of Business

Managing IT Projects course, 2006

The George Washington University School of Business

IT Risk Management course, 2007

Object Partners

Groovy and Grails, 2012

Last modified: 2015/02/26